[Music]
hello everybody welcome to the
penultimate episode of this year i'm
glad to see you all welcome
and as you know today is an episode in
which i'm gonna be taking questions from
the comments and if you hear any
disturbance in the background i really
apologize
there's something going on and uh
and it's so loud it's penetrating
through the walls so any here anyhow
let me see who all is there i can see
kunal
nick hill captain steve rogers
mr53
and many other people great to see you
all great to see you all
so let us begin with the questions
just a second
okay let's begin with question number
one
and question number one is about the
james webb telescope so as you know this
telescope has just been launched a
couple of hours ago it has gone into
space it is currently doing fine
so the question is there are three
questions here many more i got so this
will represent those questions the first
one is by the newbie can you tell how
the james webb telescope is going to
work
the second question is how can the james
webb space telescope see 13.8 billion
years in the past and how is it
different from the hubble space
telescope
and the third one is the james webb
telescope will be launched in december
how different is it from the hubble
what new discoveries are we hoping to
make with it
is there anything in particular that
excites you about it
okay so what is the james webb space
telescope it's a new telescope that the
the americans nasa are sending into
space it's in partnership with the
european space agency esa the european
space agency has provided the rocket to
launch this uh
telescope the ariane 5 rocket which was
launched from central uh central america
today
so what is this telescope so it's a much
larger telescope first of all than the
herbal space telescope if you look at
the hubble space telescope it has
its primary lens has a diameter of about
two and a half meters the james webb has
a diameter of six and a half meters
that's an enormous lens okay so that's
the first difference
the second thing is that the james webb
space telescope is going to see the
universe in the infrared range
so we see light in the visible range
or you know the web gear spectrum the
hubble also mostly saw the universe in
the visible light in the web gears
spectrum and a little bit more here and
there
this new telescope the james webb
telescope is going to see the universe
in mostly in the infrared range and some
some of the wavelengths will be in the
visible range orange onwards so it's
going to see the universe in a
completely different way in the infrared
wavelength and that is very interesting
because there's a very good reason for
doing that
and that is why it's being called a time
machine it's going to be able to look
back into the history of the universe or
almost at the to the beginning of when
the universe formed after the big bang
and the reason for that is that
in the very early universe when the
first galaxies were formed the light
that went out in all directions it has
taken
more than 13 billion years to reach us
and it has traveled through a lot of
space and the space time has been
expanding
in those
light waves
they have also been stretched out
over time over the billions of years so
light which may have started as
ultraviolet right light for example has
been over the years stretched out
stretched out stretched out and it has
become it has gone deep into the
infrared wavelengths now so it's not
possible for an ordinary telescope to
see those wavelengths and that's why
this telescope is going to do the job
and it's going to see things which uh
essentially date back to the very almost
the very beginning of the universe the
first galaxies the first stars and all
that so it's going to be able to do it
because it sees in the infrared
wavelength now
the thing is that infrared
ray infrared wavelengths are available
all around us it is essentially what we
call heat waves
our bodies give off heat the earth gives
off heat the sun gives off heat and all
of this
is infrared waves and therefore if you
put a telescope in earth orbit it's
going to be swamped with all this
infrared noise and it won't be able to
detect the very very faint
wavelengths that come from the beginning
of the universe and that's why this
telescope is being sent to a place far
away from the earth
one and a half million kilometers away
from earth at the l2 lagrange point and
it's going to be shielded from the uh
sunlight and everything by this uh by by
a
special
light shield essentially heat shield and
it's going to be cooled to around 40
degrees kelvin which is about 233
minus 233 degrees celsius so it's going
to be cooled to around that temperature
because it will be shielded from all
this light and everything and then it's
going to be able to make those uh
observations it is about a 10-year
lifespan so it's going to be able to
peer back into the very beginning of the
universe now it's a very perilous
journey it has just started it is going
to take another 29 days to reach its
destination and is going to go into
orbit around the destination the l2
lagrange point and it's going to have to
uh unfurl itself because it is so large
it cannot fit inside the rocket so they
had to create
a lens that can be folded in an entire
spacecraft that can be folded into a
small uh
space so now it will have to unfold
itself and there are lots of potential
failure points in that so it's going to
be a very tricky next 29 days and it's
going to start doing the observations
only six months down the down the line
when everything is calibrated and set so
right now the journey is still going on
it's still a way it's going to be like
uh six months of terror
because it's a very expensive telescope
it's like 25 years in the making it cost
10 billion dollars there's been so much
testing and all that and we we hope it
doesn't fail so there is still a long
way to go for the telescope to become
operational but the journey has now
finally begun so that is what the james
webb telescope is about and that's what
it's going to do it's very exciting
because it's going to
show us things we have never seen before
it's going to peer deep back into into
the very beginning of the universe and
it's going to do some planetary science
also it's going to look at exoplanets
it's going to look at the universe in a
completely different way
so that's the exciting thing about it so
that's what i can say in short about the
james webb space telescope
okay next question
i am gypsy i want to ask which part of
india do we come from
uh the answer is very simple the gypsy
the romani people the gypsies so-called
gypsies romani people are from western
india
gujarat rajasthan and sindh mostly
some people claim they are from punjab
which is not the case that is there is
no evidence for that if you look at
their facial features if you look at
their customs if you look at the
language it is closest to the people of
western india that is gujarat rajasthan
and sindh so that's the origin of the
gypsy people of course they are all of
indian origin there's not much
difference but the place of origin is
western india
okay let's take the next question it's
by abhijit mishra
do you think the revival of kashi is the
first giant step in the resurrection of
our ancient culture
and heritage
i think it's a very good step
the
we are taking baby steps in the
resurrection of india's ancient culture
and heritage and the revival of kashi
which is just beginning i would say it's
a it's a very important and very welcome
step in the direction so for a very long
time kashi has been varanasi has been a
city of great
great it's been a very dirty city a very
congested city right
it's it's it's had this reputation of
being a very filthy place very badly
governed
very congested very narrow lanes if you
want to go to a temple you go through
very narrow lanes it's not a pleasant
experience at all
so that is now being changed and you
know the entire place is being opened up
widened out and all that
there have been some complaints on
various quarters etc about certain
things that were done but i think
overall it's it's uh it's a project to
give back the great dignity that this
great city requires
uh to free the temple from all the
narrow enclosures and encroachments and
all that now we can see the temple in
the big light and all so this is a
project that is just starting it is a
very good step i think we need to do
this in all our other great cultural
centers if you know what i mean so i
think it's a it's a very good step i
think it's a very welcome step and we
need to
take this as the first baby steps in a
very long
and extensive project of reviving our
ancient culture and heritage and of
decolonizing our civilization so it's a
it's a very good it's a very good step
okay next question
so this is by d siddhu who is the
greater king shivaji maharaj or maharaja
ranjit singh okay so how do we determine
what is the criterion for greatness
we have to go back to first principles i
always keep saying go back to first
principles so let's do it here let's
let's take this as an exercise what is
the definition of greatness
so the definition in my opinion of
greatness is the maximum you
the more
you
the more of an impact you have on more
people that the the greater you are so
greatness can be good it can be bad for
example
killed 80 million people that was a huge
impact but his greatness was
was evil greatness right
what's his name uh stalin he also did he
was also you can say is a great person
he's his career impacted a lot of people
but the impact was negative to a great
extent so that again is greatness but
it's not the right kind of greatness
now let's let's take a look at these two
uh
kings in ancient india in in more recent
india
so
shivaji
shivaji maharaja
lived from from 1630 to 1680 he died
at the age of 50 very young
and what was his impact so when he died
the maratha empire was still quite small
but the maratha empire after his death
rose and rose and rose and it
it continued until i one could say the
anglo-maratha was six around 18 18 18 18
20 thereabouts so about 140 years after
he died the maratha empire continued it
grew to a great extent it encompassed
almost the whole of india and parts of
afghanistan so the
the framework that he created the
administrative and military framework
that he created it
it enabled his successors
to take the empire to incredible
greatness so that is the impact of
shatrapati shivaji maharaja even though
he died young his impact was was
significant it was a monumental impact
right
so his empire the empire he founded
continued to grow it reached an enormous
extent and it lasted uh approximately a
century and a half after he died
now let's look at maharaja ranjit singh
he lived from 1780 to 1839 right he
founded the sikh empire in 1799
and the
sick empire disintegrated within 10
years of his death
and the it's called the empire but
actually it's just a kingdom it was uh
it was a punjab some parts of kashmir in
some parts of afghanistan that's it it
was small compared to the maratha empire
so the impact of chhatrapati shivaji
maharaja is way way way greater orders
of magnitude greater than that of
maharaja ranjit thing i'm not saying
that maharaja ranjit singh was not a
great king he was a very great very good
king i admire his policies and the the
the actions he took but if you look at
the overall impact of greatness of these
two gentlemen ma um
in greatness in his positive impact
over the indian
nation over the indian civilization so i
would say the greater king is shivaji
maharaj that is my assessment
based on what i just uh on the criteria
i just laid out
okay next question it's a couple of
questions in one nil mehta says what are
your views on the theory that an ancient
civilization existed before the last ice
age 11 600 years ago when a cataclysmic
event took place and destroyed most of
it
and the sahara desert was a forest
around the time and the civilization
existed too
and the second question is please pick
my question for once
do you think civilizational resets
happened before like hancock graham
hancock suggests
if yes if it happens again can we how
can we protect our scientific
technological knowledge and cultural
heritage uh and so on so forth okay so
what are my views on the theory that an
ancient civilization existed before the
ice age look if you look at india's
genetics if you look at the history of
the indian subcontinent
the genetic lineages that we have in
india are very ancient they are if you
look at the the very very famous r1a1a
heritage lineage haplogroup it is
between 17 000 to twenty six twenty
seven twenty eight thousand years old
which way predates
this characteristic event this
hypothesized caterpillar has been given
so which is called the younger driest
event
so what we know is that there was a
certain resurgence in the ice age around
11 600 years ago it is believed to be
because of a number of possible criter
of possible
things that may have happened including
an impact event a comet or an asteroid
hitting the earth we have found some
evidence of that in greenland etc so it
looks like something happened on in our
planet
right some kind of impact event or
something like that which caused a
resurgence of the ice age which was
slowly going away so this happened
around 11 600 years ago but if that
happened it certainly did happen but it
doesn't seem to have had any effect on
india because our lineages have
continued unbroken
right if you look at the archaeology of
india of course we have not looked that
far our archaeologists are sleeping but
we have found no evil no no evidence of
some kind of reset happening in india
right and our lineages have continued
unabated
so it looks like if something like this
happened there was not much of an effect
on india there must have been some uh
coastal effect if there was an upsurge
in water levels or something but we
still don't have sufficient data in
india but the lineages have continued
unabated unchanged unbroken which means
that there was no uh
there was no dying off or any such
climatic uh event
so then uh
is it possible some ancient civilization
would have existed before the ice age in
the case of india the civilization
civilization continues
in other places it is possible that a
civilization may have existed somewhere
maybe in europe maybe in north america
central america southern america and
maybe possibly it may have died off it
is certainly possible do we have
evidence of that we do not have evidence
of that but it is certainly possible
that such events can happen and an
existing civilization can be wiped out
and we may lose all all the evidence of
that it is certainly possible so i think
that answers uh
both the questions to some extent right
so um
and what can we do if it happens again
to protect our scientific technological
knowledge cultural heritage etc
well in the case of an unforeseen
natural event like an asteroid strike
comet strike a massive earthquake
there's nothing much we can do you know
i mean certain certain events are just
way too powerful and our technology is
just so puny that it won't be able to do
much about it if you can see
a comet heading in our direction then
maybe we can deflect it or diverts or
divert its uh path its trajectory that
is certainly possible but if we find it
too late then we won't have much time to
do anything about it right so there are
certain um precautionary measures
in place
we are tracking the various known
near-earth asteroids we keep an eye on
the skies and see if any new comet is
coming our way all those things are done
and hopefully that should be uh enough
hopefully
so uh that's what we can do about it but
in case a comet even uh impact is going
to happen there's not much we can do to
you know preserve things so we are still
in in the infancy of technology and all
that so it is still a little early for
us
to be able
to uh
insulate ourselves properly from a major
cataclysmic event like that
okay next question is by dr saurabh
i want to take india back to its
glorious form
so what would be better
joining an already established political
party or creating a new organization to
mobilize people
well that's an interesting question the
thing is that if you want to create a
new organization
that is like you're starting from
scratch
you're starting from scratch you have to
create a network of people you have to
raise funds
you have to establish a leadership
structure
you have to
there's a lot of work that goes into
creating a new organization it's like a
political startup that you're talking
about right
and if you join an already established
political party you get all the benefits
of the already existing uh structures
the power structure the networks of
people uh the finances that you need to
run a political campaign all that you
get the benefit of all of that right
away you just join the political party
but the drawback is that you will have
to buy into
the political system the ideology that
already exists so then you have to go
and find a political party that is the
closest to whatever you believe in and
then you need to fit into it somehow and
you may have to rise up the ranks slowly
because it will already have leadership
and all that so yeah that that makes it
a little harder but starting a political
movement or party from scratch is even
harder because you're starting
essentially from zero with no money no
funding no networks no contacts you're
starting from zero
so i think
if you want to take the path c in any
endeavor you must take the path of least
resistance the shortest
the shortest different distance between
two points is a straight line now in
life there are no straight lines you
have to take winding paths and the
winding road sometimes
but you should
look at the bigger picture in mind you
should keep the bigger picture in mind
what's the big objective and then trying
to find
the best way of reaching it
so in case you don't agree with any
existing political ideology then you may
have to start a new political party for
which i
i would say all the best but uh
typically you would want to join an
existing political party or movement
whichever
suits you best and try to work within
that and rise to the
position that you deem
is the right position for you to make a
difference
so there are two options i think the
joining an existing political party
would be an easier option as long as its
ideology and the worldview
it is similar to that that you have
okay
next question is by avinash
could there be stars and planets made
from anti-matter anti-matter so
anti-matter is the mirror opposite of
regular matter everything is opposite
all the quantum numbers are opposite the
charges are opposite and all so on so
instead of a of a of a proton you will
have an antiproton
which is the which has the opposite
charge of a proton proton is positively
charged
anti proton is negatively charged
um instead of electrons you'll have
positrons which are positively charged
and so on and so forth so it is
certainly possible to create atoms from
antimatter and
if you can create atoms from antimatter
you can create entire stars and planets
from antimatter the only thing is that
we don't see any evidence of antimatter
any significant evidence of antimatter
in the universe we do find a positrons
we do find anti-protons from from cosmic
rays and all that but we haven't never
seen a large scale structure that is
that is clearly made up of antimatter
it's certainly hypothetically
theoretically possible there is nothing
in the laws of physics that says that
you cannot have stars and planets made
from antimatter it is hypothesized that
when the big bang happened there may
have been two major universes that were
created a pos
a
a universe made of ordinary matter the
one that we live in and a mirror
universe made of antimatter
you know so so that sort of thing in
that case everything there would be made
of antimatter stars planets galaxies
etc so it is certainly possible there is
nothing in the laws of physics that says
that this cannot happen we can certainly
envisage a universe in which you would
have this possibly even in our own
universe
okay this is by debraj
how does the amazon forest catch fire
so there are two there are multiple
mechanisms of forest catching fire
one big spectrum of mechanisms is
natural mechanisms or lightning strike
or or dry climate and then you have some
event that causes a spark which which uh
makes the forest catch fire so these are
there's a bunch of natural mechanisms by
which a forest can catch fire the second
mechanism
is that it is set by human hands the
fire is set by human hands so mostly
that's what's happening in the amazon
rainforest in in mostly in brazil what's
happening is that people are trying to
clear the rain forest to make way for uh
for plantations etc because they want to
monetize the land you know they
took it to clear new land and grow crops
and plantations over there essentially
what's happening is that they are
growing soybeans for animal agriculture
in the united states in north america
you have this enormous industry of
animal agriculture essentially beef the
beef industry and what do you feed beef
use feed the beef soy beans and you need
large amounts of land to grow all those
soybeans so what they're doing in south
america in brazil is that they're
clearing the amazon rainforest
destroying the rainforest and planting
soybeans there so for that they are
setting these certain farmers etc
prospectors you could say are setting
the forest deliberately on fire clearing
big patches of land and then using that
for farmland so mainly that's what we
are witnessing right now the amazon
forest is being set on fire repeatedly
by human hands
okay this is by vishal
do you think that china is better off
earning profits from indian companies
and strengthening its own economy rather
than fighting a war over petty
territorial disputes
if china wants to fight a war over
territory it would most likely be a
proxy war including pakistan army-backed
terrorists rather than a full-fledged
one
china has many strategic and
geographical disadvantages in the
himalayan region most of its air bases
are in the southeast region of the
mainland close to the south china sea in
taiwan
see what we see right now
what do we see right now is that china
is engaging in
various kinds of warfare not simply
the salami slicing tactics on the border
regions and in the south china sea etc
it is also engaging
in what is known as trade warfare and if
you if you examine the kind of trade
relationship india and china have china
is using india as a source for raw
materials and it is importing raw
materials essentially from india and it
is exporting back processed and finished
goods to india so this is the kind of
thing the east india company was doing
to india it was using india it destroyed
india's industries it was using india
for raw materials
and it was getting those raw materials
for very cheap and then it was sending
it was selling back finished goods to
india and that's how it was draining
india's wealth out of india now
similarly china right now has a very big
trade surplus with india i think it's in
the
60 70 80 maybe 90 billion dollars per
year that sort of thing
so that is a very good strategy why do
you need to go to war with india when
you can enjoy this wonderful trade
surplus with india and then whatever
money they are extracting out of india
in this manner they can redivert it into
pakistan and other places to bleed india
in a variety of ways so that so
essentially what's happening right now
is that india is funding china's
anti-india activities by allowing china
to enter into this to to have this major
significant massive trade surplus with
india
so that is a strategy the chinese have
been employing for for several years for
for close to two decades i would say
when they have since when they have had
this trade surplus with us so it's
strengthening china's economy
it is allowing the chinese to use
india's own money against india
and when it comes to fighting a war the
chinese will not just go to war for just
like that
they will go to war if and only if they
are convinced that it is going to be
something that they are going to win
right now if they go to war with india
they may end up getting a bloody nose
and that's why they will just keep on
needling india and the northern border
uh pressurizing india by having these
big troop concentrations in tibet and so
on and so forth and trying to make small
land grabs and all that a few 100 meters
here a few hundred meters there that's
the that's been the strategy since the
1960s and the strategy still exists they
are essentially
escalating below the threshold there is
a certain threshold that leads to war
you keep on escalating the the
situation just below the threshold for
war and that's how you just keep on
going you keep on grabbing a few inches
here and there salam is slicing very
thin slices
so that is the the strategy that the
chinese have adopted it's a very uh
successful strategy so thus far
now india has really toughened up its
stance on the border india is building
roads it's india is building its
networks infrastructure
very rapidly so now the chinese are not
happy about that and that's why the
the there has been further escalation on
the border like the galwan clash etc
so that is what the chinese are doing
you are right they have some
disadvantages in the himalayan
region but they also have certain
advantages for instance uh
most of their airfields like you say are
far away but they have also built
airfields in tibet
so there are a couple of major air bases
they have in tibet and the other
advantage they have is that their entire
population center is far far far away
from the indian border right
tibet is almost empty so so there's
nothing india can really hit and destroy
in tibet
so that is the
uh advantage and disadvantage you could
say at the same time that the chinese
have in tibet so that is the situation
so right now i don't see the chinese
fighting any war and the territorial
disputes are not really petty for the
chinese it may be small for india it is
significant because
they want indian territory they want
arunachal pradesh they want they have
already taken aksai chin in 1962
and they also hold a certain portion of
kashmir these are not trivial or petty
territorial disputes as far as india is
concerned
right
now uh so so that is the situation they
will certainly not go to war right now
unless they feel that they are
guaranteed to win it
so it is all a long term well thought
out strategy that they have and india's
strategy has to be very clear that in
the next 20 years or so india needs to
somehow engineer
the independence again of tibet if that
is done then the entire northern border
will be peaceful again so that is has to
be the long term plan that india has and
right now we are very far from that
because we are not in a strong situation
uh the way we would like to be in the
way we should we need to be in in order
to break tibet away from china so that's
where we are at
now at present
okay this is akash the insides and
outsides of the houses and buildings of
towns and cities where we live
affect people mentally the modern
architecture its design looks
specifically made to make people
depressed and gloomy is it right
the houses of old times not just
restricted to india but european
european houses too also looked way
better compared to let's say new york
city apartments which are like gilded
cages what are the possible reasons
behind this
the thing is first of all in the past we
had
a much
lower population than what we have today
today the world's population is just
exploding right so that's why we are
forced to build
vertically in the past we had the
horizontal style
layout of cities where you would have
two two story three storage buildings
and all that like we had in the uh
saraswati sindhu era of our civilization
we had multiple storage buildings but
those were just few and far between only
in the major cities
and most houses would be spread
horizontally not vertically and the most
you would have would be like three
storage or maybe four storage buildings
not more than that and the houses were
laid out according to a certain plan
it is called vastu shastra in in india i
believe in other places also they had
certain rules for for the layout of a
house so you it would ensure that the
windows were big the sunlight would come
into the house every day today you have
these apartments in india and other
countries where you never get to see the
sun there's no sunlight all the lighting
is artificial there's not enough winds
air circulation lots of problems so what
what's happening now is that you are
building these modular apartments
modular houses there are like match
boxes that people can just go and uh you
know live in just exist in there's no
living there
so that's what's happening you know i
mean everything is being commodified
everything is being cheapened it is all
about profits so real estate is all
about about profits today
you have a piece of land you raise a 50
started building there and sell these
little matchboxes to people at
exorbitant rates and you make a lot of
money out of it that's what's going on
in india and other countries so yes it
is not designed
the entire
uh
emphasis is on profits today there is no
emphasis on well-being of people on the
physical and mental well-being of people
it makes a huge difference to see the
sunlight every day and if you don't see
sunlight every day you're gonna get
depressed and gloomy and all that so yes
we have lost touch with our history with
our culture our culture not only in
india also in europe like you say it had
a certain way of doing things
and it ensured the well-being of people
but today that is simply not the
not of a point of focus at all and
that's why you find all these people
today this entire epidemic of mental
illness and mental issues
and
all that so yes yes you are absolutely
right the possible reasons it's just
that everything is commercialized now
and the only focus is on profits
everything is about profits human lives
are also to be used as commodities and
to be
profited off so this is the essential
thing about capitalism it's all about
quarter upon quarter profits endless
never-ending profits nothing else
matters the quarterly uh balance sheet
that's all that matters this the stock
port the the stock market uh
rankings etc that's what matters
so that is the reason why we have all
these problems having what we face today
everything is commodified human lives
are also commodities
everything is to be uh used for profit
so that's unfortunately why we are in
this situation
today okay this is by archit
uh what according to you is the best way
to gamify the learning of sanskrit i
personally think making an a making a
fun app like duolingo but with a much
higher focus on the elements of sanskrit
could be a fun way what do you think
so today gamification is a very big
thing gamification means the
introduction of game playing elements
into non-game playing environments like
websites like apps and all that so let's
say you have an educational app which is
actually a serious app for learning
something but if you
gamify the app and you introduce
elements of game playing challenges
levels and all that then it makes it a
much more interesting and fun experience
so that is gamification so how do you
gamify the learning of sanskrit well
like you said you need to make a fun app
which has levels which has challenges
maybe you can even make it multiplayer
if you can think of a way to do that
right i haven't seen duolingo i've heard
of it it's a it's a language learning
app yes
so yeah something like that needs to be
done i mean i cannot give the best
possible way of doing it but certainly
one can brainstorm different ways
of of gamifying learning a language
and sanskrit obviously it's a very
structured language so it would be
easier to structure the gamification of
the app so what i would say needs to be
done is
we need to create an app
which has elements of game playing which
has levels which has challenges which
may be multiplayer and the thing is this
see
it's uh not only apps that that promote
languages it is things like uh it is
things like
anime for instance and entire games
themselves that that can promote culture
and languages if you look at japanese
anime it has done so much to promote
japanese culture and the japanese
language
across the world japanese enemy and the
games that the japanese designers make
that those have been so influential in
promoting japanese culture and people
find it very cool to learn japanese
right today sanskrit is not cool because
there is nothing like that in sanskrit
there are no games in which which have
elements of sanskrit and elements of
indian culture and there are no
animations enemies and all that
uh that again have any elements of
sanskrit in culture and again no apps so
so these things can be thought about
and they can certainly be incorporated
and
and gamification can be incorporated in
an app
to learn sanskrit
okay why is venus hotter than mercury
why is he venus hotter than mercury so
if you look at the uh
the planet mercury it is the closest
planet to the sun in the entire solar
system and it's very hot i mean if when
you
the the
side that faces the sun is like around
700 degrees celsius i'm just
doing a ballpark thing here around 700
plus degrees celsius and the side that
is not facing the sun will be like minus
200 or so perhaps degree celsius so it's
an extreme environment but the side that
faces the sun is really hot maybe not
700 maybe something less but it's quite
hot but venus is even hotter
than the side of mercury that was any at
any given time facing the sun why is it
so and the reason is excuse me it's
because of the atmosphere
of venus
so the atmosphere of venus is more than
90 more than 94 95 made up of carbon
dioxide now carbon dioxide is what we
call a greenhouse gas it is a gas that
absorbs heat and traps heat so when you
have an atmosphere that's made up of
more than 90 carbon dioxide it's going
to cause a runaway greenhouse effect
it's it just absorbs the heat from the
rays of the sun from the sunlight and it
traps it within the atmosphere it is not
a the atmosphere doesn't release that
heat so the atmosphere over time has
become hotter and hotter and hotter it
is hot enough to melt lead on the
surface of venus now venus has an
enormously thick atmosphere the volume
the the mass of the atmosphere is like
90 times more than 90 times the mass of
earth's atmosphere
and the thickness uh the atmospheric
pressure is also more than 90 times the
atmospheric pressure of earth
and it's all mostly carbon dioxide more
than 94 95 carbon dioxide so all these
conditions have created this enormous
runaway greenhouse effect on the planet
and that is why the temperature is so
incredibly high on the surface of the
planet or inside the atmosphere it is
hot enough to melt
lead which is a metal which is
incredible so that's why venus is the
hottest planet in the solar system it is
even hotter than mercury
okay the next question is by dungar
singh chauhan
what are your views on the anti
antikythera mechanism found in greece
so the antikythera mechanism is a
so let's let's take a look at what this
mechanism looks like let me share my
screen the antiquity theorem mechanism
we will go to google and take a look at
that let me put google on
here we are
mechanism here it is and let's go to
images
so this is
an artifact that was found by
archaeologists about 100 plus years ago
in a shipwreck
of a greek island called antique terra
so this is a very interesting mechanism
it's it's clearly a dial it's not just
one dial
it's an entire cog and dial structure if
you can and if you see the
reconstruction it looks something like
this something like this so it's so it's
more than 2000 years old it's a very
intricate mechanism with lots of
interlocking
dials and levers and all that and what
this mechanism was
was it was a device that would allow you
to uh
to keep time it was a time measurement
mechanism it would allow you to predict
solar and the lunar eclipses in the
future it is also something that would
allow you to track the olympic games
which were held once every four years
it was also a navigation mechanism it
would allow you to navigate where you
are based on the date and all that
uh so so that's what it was it was a
navigational and
mechanism a very intricate thing it is
in some ways more intricate than the
clockwork you have in modern day clocks
so it's very interesting that the greeks
more than 2000 years ago were able to
create a mechanism that was that that
was this
complex
and this accurate it has been recreated
reconstructed uh in the present day so
what happened is that for a very long
time the entire thing was like rusted
and it was filled filled with sediment
and it would not be
we could not look inside it what what it
was like but in the 21st century because
of uh various techniques i think it was
it's not
i think it was a position mission
tomography or something positron
emission tomography or one of these
techniques one of these uh tools that
enabled us to look inside the mechanism
and see its internal structure and
that's how we
been able to recreate this entire
mechanism and see how it works so it was
a very very very complex mechanism and
surprisingly very accurate so that is
what this antikythera mechanism was
all right let's go on to the next
question
this is by raghav singh
why our historians do not consider the
historical records of the bards the bots
as a reliable source for writing the
history
i am a tanworth rajput
migrations in the following way which
even gives an indication that the
rajputs probably migrated into india but
not natives
the entire history is there so what are
my views about it so the thing is that
when you want to um
when you want to record the history of a
place you have to take into
consideration all the possible sources
of history you have oral sources you
have written records you have
archaeology you have other other
epigraphic sources literature everything
that's available has to be considered
seriously and then based on all the data
points and all the elements of data that
you have you come to an informed and
educated understanding of what the
history of a certain place certain
region certain lineage certain culture
was like
now india's marxist historians they
summarily uh dis discard certain aspects
of of indian historiography for instance
you have oral records which are said
that which they say that they're all
myths and legends we cannot consider
them to be in any way accurate so the
one of the one of the major ways of
recording uh ancient events in the past
especially among the rajputs was the
stories of the of the bards the bats or
the charms they were called also right
so they would record the history of
various families of various clans
for centuries there would be families of
these people who would do it generation
after generation and i'm sure these
records still exist in some places
and yet these are completely disregarded
by by historians i don't think
historians have even bothered to look
into these records that may still exist
in various places in various families
and that's why these uh
ancient uh these the these ancient
records of indian history are completely
disrupt disregarded and that's why we
are missing big big chunks and big
elements of indian history especially in
western india in the in the
rajput
regions of india which were in the past
ruled by rajputs so i think that it is
very important that we should take all
possible sources of information
into consideration including the records
of the birds of the parts of the charans
etc because i think there's a wealth of
information that we can extract
from these records
and once again there is another source
of records which is the jain records the
jain uh sources have also been recording
history for for like i would say
thousands of years i think there are
places where
uh
there are
most likely still existing records from
a thousand plus years back among among
the jain collections i think that also
should be looked into if it is still
available so there are many sources of
information that have completely been
been neglected that would certainly
enrich india's understanding of its
history so i think it needs to happen it
would it would be very good if
present-day historians or future
historians would look into these sources
as well
okay this is by pink line cabs
suppose the indian economic growth
matches the chinese economy in the
coming years
as china has trapped many countries in
its debt trap
how could india liberate these stuck
countries sri lanka nigeria other
countries etc
okay so first of all we are not sure of
how india's economic growth is going to
go i am hoping it is going to be 10
plus in the next 20 years which will
enable india to to eventually quickly in
the next two decades grow to a
middle-income
country for that we will need double
digit growth for around two decades so
that is a big ask hopefully it happens
now what about the debt trap so what is
the debt trap right everyone talks about
the debt trap
the that the debt trap is this the
chinese they offer loans
to uh
various
low-income countries what is now what is
what is known as third world countries
especially like you mentioned sri lanka
nigeria other african countries what
they do is that they offer these big
loans
ostensibly for national development for
certain projects infrastructure projects
development projects they offer these
big loans and the terms of the loan are
terrible like very very high interest
rates and all that
and these countries for some reason they
accept those uh those those terms and
what happens is that after whenever the
money is due they are unable to repay
the money because the interest rates and
all that is so high and then the chinese
what they do is that they nationalize
the they don't nationalize the project
but they essentially take over that
piece of land that project or whatever
and they essentially own it so that's
what's happening in sri lanka
that's what's happening in various parts
of africa the question is why do these
countries accept such onerous loan
conditions and the answer is very simple
these are third world countries they are
essentially run by dictatorships or
something similar to that so it's very
easy
to bribe the person who is in charge of
the show
to bribe whoever the the
president or prime minister or dictator
and then offer this loan that guy will
get whatever he wants his big piece of
money his big piece of the pie and then
eventually he'll be gone and his country
will have to
bear the burden of the loan that they
cannot repay
so the chinese are using that to to
essentially colonize
various parts of the world especially
the third world countries so that is the
chinese debt trap the sri lankans have
fallen into that
surprise
various african countries are falling
into that and so on and so forth the
question is how could india liberate the
stuck countries my my question is why
should india liberate this constructor
is is india on a on a mission to
liberate the world
india has its own problems
geopolitics is a game in which you look
out for yourself
and you align with other countries that
have interests that are that match yours
you don't go giving free lunches to the
world that's not how the world works the
question is why should india bother to
liberate these countries we did not put
them in that hole they dug the hole for
themselves and went into that it is for
them to extricate themselves from the
world now
what india can do is india can
uh diplomatically engage with lots of
countries especially in the african
region etc and develop its own
relationships with various countries but
india should not offer to extricate
countries by giving them free money that
simply doesn't work there is no free
lunch in the world there is no free
lunch in the geopolitical in geopolitics
india does not need to bother with
liberating countries which are in
trouble when india is in trouble does
anybody come to to help india nobody
does so that is not how the world works
when you dig a hole and you jump into
that hole you have to extricate yourself
these countries went into this willingly
it is for them to find a way to
extricate themselves out of it of course
the chinese influence is growing and we
need to find other ways
of of
of countering the growing chinese
influence so for that indian is to
become a much more
powerful country a much bigger economy
and then
play the geopolitical game at a certain
level but india
in my opinion should not even waste a
minute trying to thinking about how to
liberate the world and make the world a
better place and all that no look out
for yourself because that is how the
game is played
okay next question next question
sohit kumar singh says
what are the challenges for a 21 year
old aspiring to build a space elevator
in india
with the help of government or privately
since china and america are planning to
build by 2040 i aspire to build it by
2035. so i am not aware of any uh i mean
see i don't know everything in the world
so i am not aware of any chinese plants
or american plants to build a space
elevator by whatever year so the
question first of all is what is a space
elevator
a space elevator is a big structure
which is more than 36 000 kilometers
long
in which you have one end which is in
orbit around the earth uh
beyond the geostationary orbit uh limit
and the other end is tethered in the
earth itself
and the whole thing goes round and round
like if you had a string and you were
welding it round so that's what a space
elevator is
so it is there is a there is a
counterweight up in space beyond 36 000
kilometers
uh an anchor point in the in the earth
itself which will uh hold this thing
together and a long tether a long tether
that is more than thirty six thousand
kilometers long it needs to be made of a
material that can withstand that
incredible strain that incredible stress
it should be able to withstand the the
possible effect of micro meteorites of
space debris it should also be able to
withstand the corrosion of the earth's
atmosphere and as far as we know no such
material exists
that has those qualities right so as of
today the technology doesn't exist to
build a space elevator and then even if
you have the technology you would have
to create this incredibly
enormous
structure we don't have the space
launched capability to do that and it
would cost possibly hundreds of billions
of dollars to create a structure like
that like that at least tens of billions
of dollars even if we had the technology
so if you want to build a space
elevator so first of all you need to be
a multi-billionaire okay that is the
first criterion you need to have you
need to be a multi-billionaire then you
need to be able to do the rnd you need
to have the rnd capabilities to uh
develop a material which doesn't exist
because that material will need to need
to be able to withstand incredible uh
tension
and it needs to be resistant to
corrosion resistant to micro meteorite
and space debris impacts and all those
things
so there's a lot that you need to
develop a lot of technology that you
need to develop in the next 15 years but
first of all you will have to become a
multi-billionaire will the government of
india be interested in such a project i
doubt it very much this is a very
speculative futuristic technology you
will have to sink in tens of billions of
dollars into the research and the
development and there's only one chance
at building it right because if you
build a space tether a space uh elevator
and it breaks it's going to have a
devastating impact on
or from the space debris perspective
right so there's there's a very big
challenge when it come when it comes to
building a space elevator i do not see
it being built anytime by 2040 maybe not
in the next 50 years it is a very
interesting hypothetical
theoretical thing
it is certainly feasible if you have um
the material and the technology to build
it what can actually be done
is you can build a space elevator
on the moon
over there the geostationary limit is
the geostation geostationary distance is
much less than 36 000 kilometers and the
tensile strength you will need will be
much less so i think materials like
kevlar etc may actually fit the bill of
the of the material of the tether so
what can be done is possibly one can put
one can try to build a space elevator
around the moon that would be much
easier and it is certainly
possible possibly
using the present-day technology that we
have at least the material is already
available
so that is the challenge and that's what
needs to be done and
from my perspective it is
nearly impossible
to even
think of a space elevator by 2040
and even if you have this challenging
target that you will do it by 2035 you
need to first become a multi-billionaire
do not expect any government support and
then after you have become a
multi-billionaire you will need to very
quickly develop the technology to put
this into place so it's a monumental
challenge i'm not saying it's impossible
but it's a monumental monumental
challenge i am sure there are other
things if you become multi-billionaire
that you can invest your time into which
will be more feasible and which may give
you a better return on investment and be
actually beneficial to the world at
large so that's the that's the
scenario that you have to consider and
those are the different uh
challenges that you will face in the
mission of
of of constructing a space elevator
okay the next question is by karthik
srinivas what makes some scientists
believe that we are living in a
simulation why do we feel pain if you
live in a simulation
what is the simulation hypothesis the
simulation hypothesis is that the entire
universe that we live in is actually
a simulation inside a super inside a
hyper computer which is run by some very
intelligent species of aliens so that is
the simulation hypothesis why do people
take it seriously because it is entirely
plausible
it is entirely possible there is nothing
in science that says that we cannot be
living in a simulation
so it is certainly plausible that it may
be it may be a simulation that we're
living in
right
so uh
and the thing is this see
everything that we uh
that we can see around us everything
that we can imagine around us if we have
high enough computing power it can be
generated inside a computer if you look
at the games
that we have today let's let's look at
the games that we had in the 1980s those
were very basic games very very uh very
basic graphics very pixelated and very
rough graphics but as the years went by
the graphics got better and better and
more realistic
today if you play an xbox game a
playstation 5 game or some other games
it looks very realistic so you can
create entire worlds inside the game
environment inside your computer right
you can do that
and if you have a super computer you can
actually uh you can actually model the
universe to some extent you know with
the laws of physics and everything
inside the supercomputer so it's like
the universe is evolving a small portion
of the universe is evolving
inside the computer itself so it is
certainly plausible that you have if you
have a massive enough computer let's say
if you have a matryoshka brain size
computer which can let's say carry out
10 raised to 40 computations per second
it is certainly possible to create a
completely realistic world
with people inside it the only
assumption that we have to make is that
you can actually simulate consciousness
which we don't know about but if if that
assumption holds true then you can
certainly simulate an entire universe a
very realistic
very very real universe inside a
computer of that scale a matrix
scale computer
so that is why
some scientists believe that we may
possibly perhaps be living inside a
simulation and and that that
that is
certainly plausible there is nothing
incorrect about
that assumption that is this may be
possible i am not saying we are living
in a simulation we don't know
if you are inside you will never know
what's outside right
but
it is certainly plausible
that it may be the case
okay this is by harpreet why is the west
favorable or neutral towards buddhism
and east asian cultures
and hostile towards indian culture even
discounting the sympathy towards tibet
and the dalai lama they are also
idolaters yet these are promoted as
something very nice and desirable many
in india get influenced by that
see most people in the west don't don't
know anything about india they
they are essentially informed and
influenced by the media
by the media and the establishment so
whatever is the prevailing attitude in
the media and the establishment they
will simply imbibe and absorb those
attitudes and that's what shapes their
worldview so
it's not their fault that they have
absorbed all that because that's the
environment they live in now if you look
at the west what really runs the west if
you look at uh what what is behind the
media the media in the west you will
find that a lot of it is funded by the
catholic church and various christian
organizations there are other
organizations also that are inimical to
india
and
india is the last
refuge of polytheism of the ancient
indo-european indian culture
indo-european culture so 2000 years ago
indo-european culture was spread across
eurasia from india in the east all the
way to ireland in the west that was all
wiped out stamped out of europe by uh by
christianity it is very well known very
well recorded there is no controversy in
that right now india is the last rank uh
stronghold
so to say it's not very strong anymore
but hinduism still exists in india
and if india can that if if that culture
can be erased from india then india can
be manipulated in a variety of ways
essentially india can be used as a big
captive market from which money can be
extracted out of and stiffened out of
so the key is to eradicate hinduism from
india and how do you do it by demonizing
hinduism the first thing they will say
is caste cast cast
indians themselves stupidly enough
believe that their their culture is bad
the culture is evil we are castes we are
we have been oppressing the minorities
we have been oppressing each other
this
sentiment is so deeply ingrained in the
indians themselves that they are so
diffident they are so uh
they lack self-confident confidence
they don't have any real love for the
culture so it's working you know
and the same tropes
are prevalent in the western media that
hinduism is all about caste operation
hinduism is all about patriarchy
hinduism is all about burning women and
so on and so forth so because of these
attitudes that have been prevalent for
at least 200 years from the colonial
days because the missionaries created
these are these uh
these uh stories these narratives so all
that is deeply prevalent in in the west
and that's why they have this feeling
towards india that is one of a great
deal of hostility so if and it's also
because of the attitude of indians who
live abroad they are very different they
don't show of their culture the way
other religions and other
ethnicities do right they will not say
i'm a proud hindu ever they'll just try
to subdue it tone it down they will
always say merry christmas to others but
they will not expect anyone to say happy
diwali to them so these are the reasons
why because of this very self-effacing
nature of indians who live in the us for
instance there are more than 3 million
indians in the u.s a significant number
but they they will never
they will never proudly show off their
culture and practice their culture they
will just try to keep it hidden and
subdued
so that that is also one of the reasons
and there is a great deal of hindu
phobia in the west great deal of
indophobia because of all these
prevalent notions and attitudes and all
that so these are some of the reasons
why they are uh
hostile towards indian culture towards
hinduism especially and there is this
project to break hinduism like i said
and buddhism
the the
identification of buddhism as a separate
religion is part of that so buddhism is
portrayed as something that is our
resistance to brahman brahmanical
oppression whatever that is
right buddhism is is was enough attempt
to reform hinduism and that's why they
show hindu the they show buddhism as
something that is desirable something
that is positive as opposed to hinduism
which is negative so these are the
various techniques they have been using
for quite some time to break hinduism
into pieces to splinter indian society
into lots of small divisions
and that's why they
portray buddhism as positive and nice
and good
and hinduism as the opposite of that as
as the
as the negative and evil
uh older religion out of which buddhism
emerged as a reform movement
so that's the overall situation and it's
just going to continue until india does
something about it
okay let's take the next question which
is by pranav pandey
when india became independent why did
they adopt a parliamentary system of
government and why not a presidential
system
also is the presidential system more
relevant than the parliamentary system
in india
when india became independent is
is not quite accurate india has never
become independent
what happened is that there was a
transfer of power from the british to a
set of people appointed by the british
they transferred power to the people
they wanted to come to power in india
they did not transfer power in a
democratic manner there was no election
of the first primary prime minister of
india the first prime minister of india
was appointed by mohandas gandhi on
behalf of the british and there was
jawal nehru the people who wrote india's
constitution were people appointed by
the british it was not
the the constituent assembly of india
was not a representative of the people
of india
many of those people were hand-picked
many of the people were elected in the
1943 election which was under foreign
occupation which means it is a
completely illegitimate election
so these are the people who framed
india's constitution who decided what
sort of system india should have
and that's why they were all people who
were hand-picked and appointed by the
british they owed their entire political
career and everything to the british and
that's why
they chose
to continue the same british system in
india the westminster parliamentary
system they uh
they continued the same laws that the
british had enacted nothing was changed
the constitution of india was was again
nothing but a consider continuation of
various uh
european constitutions and the british
and british acts and all that
so nothing changed you cannot you cannot
call that independence when you have
independence from a foreign country it
means that you throw away all their laws
all their institutions and all the
people who were who were appointed as
puppets by them and you start your own
system from scratch that is called
independence india never got
independence india is still not
independent because we are still
following the british laws the british
institutions the british parliament
system and the constitution and
everything else india is still not
independent right so that is why
the
so-called the people who are alleged to
be india's founding fathers as if india
was founded in 1947
that is why those people
they adopted the parliamentary system of
government because they were simply a
continuation of the british empire right
not the so so
the question is is the pressure
presidential system more relevant
than the parliamentary system in india
see
the system that serves your country the
best is the best system for you it is
the most relevant system for you if you
look at the parliamentary system which
is uh in place at the center and in all
the different states where you have the
state legislators what you have is chaos
you have utter chaos all we indians do
is argue argue debate debate talk talk
talk and nothing gets done you have
election after election every year so
much money is wasted in these elections
so much time is wasted in all these
pointless debates and shouting matches
and precious little gets done
the other thing is that you are not
allowed my dear friends you
are not allowed to appoint your prime
minister you are not allowed to select
your prime minister
what you are allowed to do is to vote
for your local mp and then all these mps
will get together and they will decide
who will be the prime minister
you are not allowed to to directly vote
for the prime minister of your choice
why is that
why are you denied this right
in the u.s
they have a higher house and a lower
house they have the senate and the in
the congress right
but they vote for the president directly
there is a little bit of indirectness in
that but you get to vote for whoever you
want to see as president in india you
can't do that you cannot vote for i want
this person as prime minister you can
only vote for your local mp isn't that
an injustice why are you denied the
right to decide your own prime minister
or or leader or your chief minister
you are not allowed that right
everything is indirect they are taking
power away from you
and you don't realize this you think
this is a wonderful system we get to
vote every five years or four years or
five years yeah five years in india
you don't have any say in who gets to
rule you at the end of the day
so this system is not right for india it
is just not right
the westminster democracy system
is a system that evolved over a few
centuries on a small island in the
pacific ocean
it is suitable for a small island
in europe it is not suitable for a
subcontinent-sized civilization like
india india needs its own system
the presidential system would be much
better for sure than the parliamentary
system 100 there's no doubt about it
there will be much more directness in
that system there will be much more
decision-making ability there will be
much more political stability once you
in the u.s
once you once a president is elected
he or she it's always been he thus far
he is in power for four years there is
no question of him being uh
evicted from the from the position of
president in india
if you have a coalition government your
prime minister can change every three
months
there is no political stability even
when you may not have a coalition
government still if there is a coup
within the party you may have a new
prime minister which you
may never have expected
so it is a very unstable political
system that is in place in india when
you have a big majority for one party
then things go smoothly but if you
remember the 1990s and before that and
even after that you had this horrible
coalition governments in which you had
common minimum programs which were
nothing but
what can i say it it led india nowhere
it led india backwards
no political stability everybody is
jousting for space
that is a horrible
horrible system and that's what india
has been laboring under for the past 70
plus years and india thinks oh yeah it's
the greatest democracy in the world it's
not it's a terrible messy inefficient
system that is doing more harm than good
to india in the 21st century the world
will be led by those countries but make
the fastest decisions and implement them
the fastest and in the indian system
everything takes an eternity
so the parliamentary system is not the
right system for india india needs
political stability and strong
leadership it needs a system that can
provide that if we learn the lessons of
history
that's the answer
okay
in the future
will we be able to colonize mars
then
can india shift its capital from delhi
to mars
well i don't know when we will be able
to colonize mars
we may be able to
you know the plans that elon musk has
i think he plans to have a small
presence on mars in the next 10 15 20
years at most a small colony at least
the first human footsteps of on mars
and maybe if he succeeds and things go
well then in the next 30 40 50 years
there may be a small colony of maybe 50
people hundred people maybe thousand
people on mars
hopefully india may also do something
like that i would like to see india show
some ambition in its space program which
we are not seeing any of right now but
hopefully it will happen as india
becomes economically more prosperous
prosperous
so yes maybe in the next 50 years you
may have a
thousand two thousand few thousand
people humans on mars it is possible it
is not uh
impossible to envision and visage such a
thing in the next 50 years
so it is
quite possible maybe even likely that we
will be able to colonize mars in the
future but to shift a capital city to
mars you would need at least a hundred
thousand people otherwise you can't have
a capital with 50 people right a
thousand people
so that would take a couple of centuries
perhaps to have thousands maybe millions
of people on mars
and even then even if india is able to
send let's say a million people to mars
and have its own city there
what's the point of making that city in
india's capital
a capital city should be within the
heartland within within the uh
geographical territory of the country of
the of the nation right it should be
right there
for ease of governance
you have this eight minute time lag
between earth and mars because of the
distance between earth and mars it takes
light
and radio signals and all
telecommunication communication signals
eight minutes is it eight minutes it's
something like that
uh a few minutes at least maybe four
minutes i'm not sure i don't remember
the exact number it takes a significant
amount of time for a signal to reach
mass and come back to earth
and when you have a capital city you
have a prime minister president king
emperor whatever you have there
that person needs to be able to make
decisions instantaneously
and
relay the instructions instantaneously
you cannot have a time lag
between
uh
between you receiving some information
making a decision and then relaying that
command to your subordinates so it
doesn't make sense to have a capital
city on another planet the capital city
of india should be in india if india
acquires a territory on mars we can have
a capital city of that territory on mars
but not the capital of india in mars
but it will be nice to see human
colonies on mars that will be a sight to
behold
okay
abhilash says
the other day you said that guru drona
denied education to iklavi and karna
because he was hired by the kings
as the royal creature teacher to educate
and teach the
teach the princes
what i said that he did impart some
education to karuna it's a long story so
then why is it that drona in my
vocabulary cheated
and asked for iklavia's thumb to put him
down
or more like to make
arjun the best archer in the world is it
because dorona was not capable enough to
teach arjun to the to be the best
or is it because arjun was not capable
enough to learn
to be the best you know
none of these options apply here's what
happened
dronacharya
was the royal teacher he was the royal
guru he was not the only guru in the
country there must have been hundreds of
gurus in the country who taught martial
arts so first of all there was no need
for a club via to come and ask drona
specifically for instruction
ekklavia was not the son of a king
eklavya was not a member
of the of the guru dynasty or yeah
right he was not who was aklavia see the
way ik lavia is depicted in popular
drawings etc he's depicted as a tribal
person he's depicted as wearing a tribal
dress he has feathers in his hair and
all that
that
is an attempt to mislead all of you
iklavia was the son of a general in the
army of jarasandha the king of magadha
he was
born in a prominent
warrior family
right
so the question arises why did he not
seek instruction from a guru in magadh
why did he have to come
and ask dronacharya for instruction
if a pakistani comes to india to the
indian military academy
and says give me instruction because
you have to give instruction to whoever
asks you
should we give instruction to him and
make him the best soldier in the world
why should we
magadh was the enemy
and there's this guy from magda the son
of a big general who wants to get
instruction from dronacharya why should
dronacharis shoot his own
nation his own kingdom in the foot by
doing that
that's point number one
right and secondly what happened is this
mr eklavier even though dronacharya said
that i cannot instruct you what mr
eklava did was that he quietly
stealthily
secretly
stole the knowledge from dronacharya by
observing in secret
do you think that is ethical
to mislead your guru and to steal the
knowledge he said that you are not
going to receive
do you think it is ethical what what ick
love you did
he acquired
knowledge through
treachery and therefore i do not see
anything
wrong
in what dronacharya did to him he asked
him for his thumb how was it cheating
it is mr eklavya who cheated
who stole the knowledge by treacherous
means he was denied the knowledge he
said that you will not receive knowledge
from me go somewhere else go back to
your kingdom go to some other guru and
get the knowledge there
i my job as dornacharya would say is to
teach the royal princes of my kingdom
not teach you
so
according to the law the principles of
ethics of dharma
mr eklavy should have gone back to his
kingdom and sought instruction from a
guru there
but he stole the knowledge
of dranacharya unethically
through treachery through trickery
he hacked the knowledge he stole the
knowledge
and therefore i see nothing wrong
with what
uh dronachary did to eklavya he demanded
his thumb as gurudakira because he stole
the knowledge
excellent job that's what he should have
done
it has nothing to do with arjun it has
nothing to do with karna karna is a
totally different case right people say
why did dronacharya deny certain
knowledge to karuna because he was not
worthy of the knowledge
the problem is most people get their
knowledge of history from tv serials
tv serials want to create controversies
so that they can get trps and ratings
and eyeballs
so they will try to create this
artificial cardinal versus arjun divide
and maybe karna was better but indian
history has portrayed him as as being
inferior with to malign him and all that
he has been
unfairly treated in history all that
nonsense
karna was not worthy enough to get
certain kinds of knowledge
he was a short-tempered foul-mouthed
person
he was not mentally as stable as the
greatest warriors should be
he was not worthy of receiving the
knowledge of the brahmastra
and please note
please note this
that dronacharya did not impart the
knowledge of the brahmasa even to his
own son ashwathama
so there's no question
of discrimination and all that nonsense
so i i would
i would say that uh
it is best to learn history from actual
original sources what you can do is
actually read
the history you can read the mahabharata
maybe the original sanskrit version may
be a translation into your native
language
into your mother tongue maybe a
translation into english maybe even a
smaller abridged version but at least
read the story once in written form
watching tv serials is going to mislead
you terribly
okay
next question
ah here we go
other kumari allah says do we have free
will or is free will an illusion some
neuroscientists have claimed they can
actually predict accurately predict a
person's choice by looking at the live
brain scans at least five seconds before
he makes a choice
which means that we are just biological
robots
running on ai and algorithms my your
take
okay no matter how i answer this
at least 50 of the people will disagree
with me
free will do we have free will
okay
let's let's examine this from a
different perspective let's say
we create
an artificially intelligent
computer
a computer
so it's a machine
but it has artificial intelligence and
let's say we somehow make it conscious
so it isn't it is the we have reached
the reach the singularity
right so this is a machine that can
think that is aware of itself that is
aware of the external world it can make
its own choices
and things like that so it is like an
artificial person right
does this thing have free will what has
happened is that we have created a
machine
it is a machine it is running on
hardware
and software that we created we
programmed it
and now for some reason it is acquired
free will uh it has acquired um
self awareness
right
so does this machine
have free will
so
the the functioning of this machine that
we have created it depends on the
hardware that we built
and the software that we put into it it
is all created by us the hardware is
atoms and molecules
atoms and molecules are governed by the
laws of physics
yes
the software
is all logic
again it has its own its own laws
so once again
if you
know everything about the software
package you can actually predict
its functioning
and in a physical system made of atoms
molecules etc if you know the initial
conditions
then you can predict
accurately future
conditions
uh using uh the laws of physics
essentially it's a in in the classical
sense it is all differential equations
if you know the initial conditions you
can predict conditions at any given time
in the future
so the the laws of nature the laws of
physics are deterministic now when it
comes to the microscopic world quantum
mechanics you have random uncertainties
right
but those random uncertainties are
genuinely random they are not dependent
on your will
so once again
even the laws of quantum mechanics are
deterministic with some randomness with
some genuine randomness with some
quantum jumps and all that
so if you look at the universe from this
perspective
you find that it is entirely
deterministic with some quantum
randomness thrown in the mix
so this machine
if you know if you have a big enough
computer
to calculate all the initial conditions
and all and and
the positions and all the parameters of
all the molecules etc you can
deterministically compute a future state
of the machine and you can actually
compute everything that will be going on
in that in that machine's brain
so that would indicate there is no free
will
now that machine is like this machine
the human brain
right
the human brain is also made of atoms
molecules all that it is also confined
in this in in this cranium in this space
it is also made of atoms molecules it is
also bound by the same laws of physics
it is incredibly complex and yet if you
have a computer large enough to
calculate everything you can accurately
predict every future later state of the
system
which would kind of say that there is no
free will in the universe
so according to
science according to the laws of physics
according to everything we know about
physics
free will
doesn't exist it is an illusion
everything
in the universe
could be predicted
if you know the initial conditions of
the universe at the time of the big bang
that's what it means
so according to what we understand of
the laws of physics there is no free
will
so is there any free will
what is my point my position on this my
position is
is this
that according to the laws of physics
there's no free will but we don't
understand the full laws of physics
there is so much in physics that we do
not understand
95 percent of the universe is unknown to
us we only understand
barely
five percent of the universe and we
understand even that very poorly
so according to our extremely limited
and rudimentary and poor understanding
of the laws of physics there is no free
will
but
we clearly have enormous gaps in our
knowledge
so the answer as far as i am concerned
is we don't know
from what we know there are certain
scientists who will tell you that we
know physics
and because of that there is no free
will
your emotions your thoughts are simply
chemical reactions
and that's it
the thing is we don't know
there is so much we don't know we don't
even understand how the brain works we
don't know what consciousness is
consciousness and free will
are
clearly intrinsically tied together
consciousness is an enormous enormous
mystery
uh
and there is no definition or
understanding of consciousness in
in the science that we know
the laws of physics that we that we know
have no conception of consciousness
it is a baffling phenomenon so my
um
to summarize i would say that we don't
know whether free will exists or not
according if you will just go blindly
with the little that we know about
physics then it would appear that there
is no free will but clearly there is
more to the universe than that so my
answer is
it is a mystery does free will exist is
it an illusion it is still
a mystery we don't have the answer
and i'm saying this from the from the
perspective of science if i say if i go
into the perspective of philosophy
spirituality there are all kinds of
answers which i will not go into i will
answer purely as a scientist as an
open-minded scientist that we don't know
okay chaitanya says can't it be said
that hinduism or sanatana dharma is
essentially basically an agnostic
religion
because
the hymn there is a hymn that questions
who created it all the gods were formed
afterwards who can tell it etc this
seems very different from the abrahamic
religions where the holy book declares
this happened and then that came so
hinduism clearly is very different from
the abrahamic religions
like you say in the nasa
the creation hymn of the of the rig veda
it is essentially said that we don't
know how creation happened
the gods themselves came after creation
so so what was there before creation
and and who created the universe right
and then if somebody created the
universe who created him or her
that is essentially the question that is
asked that this is a very there is a
very agnostic position to take right
so if you look at this
uh the nasa there is clearly an element
of agnosticism in the rigveda but if you
look at other portions of the rigveda we
clearly see all the extollations of the
the gods
hymns to the gods etc
so i would say that hinduism sanatana
dharma is a very complex uh
spiritual philosophical system there are
elements of everything in it there are
elements of agnosticism
there are elements of i mean there is
also the uh
in almost every philosophical school of
thought in hinduism
you have
the belief in the law of karma
uh many of the schools of thought
believe in
a supreme
soul that permeates the universe they
believe in the existence of souls a
permanent
non-destructible souls so there are lots
of different elements in sanatana dharma
there are elements of agnosticism but
there are
other parts of the vedas that would say
otherwise as well
so
it's a mixed bag it's a very complex
system it's not easy to understand and
that's why it is so
so very much
misunderstood
and misportrayed to a great deal but
like you say there is clearly an element
element of agnosticism
in this particular
sukta of the rigveda
vijay says we know all the galaxies have
a black hole at the center but what came
first galaxy or black hole it's like the
chicken and egg question what came first
so what came first galaxies or black
holes clearly black holes came first
um
in the very very early universe view it
is believed it is quite it is quite
likely that there were these microscopic
quantum fluctuations which led which
created very small tiny regions of
over density of matter or rather energy
which collapsed into black holes so it
is very likely that in the very early
universe right after the big bang there
was this massive over production of
primordial microscopic black holes
and it is theorized that it is these
primordial microscopic black holes that
eventually formed the seeds of the
supermassive black holes that are found
at the center of galaxies so if this is
correct
which is which is one of the leading
theories today so if it is correct then
it would mean that black holes came way
before
galaxies
so that's the short answer
okay next question
uchiha itachi says
uh why are we not building new
sculptures in temples like the old times
now we just make buildings for gods to
rest
not for educational purposes like before
so yeah this is something we notice
whatever newer temples are being built
they are very plain structures very very
simple structures the walls etc
if you look at the older temples that
have survived you will see incredible
sculptures on every inch of the walls
human figures human shapes
people dancing people doing things
people worshiping and more than that
right
so very very beautiful carvings of human
shapes are there on these ancient
temples even if you look at the ruins of
the original temple there was this that
was destroyed
uh
you will see this beautiful
uh carvings of human figures on that
right
if you look at the new sunnah temple i'm
not sure if there are too many carvings
of human figures on the on the walls of
the temple and if you see other newer
temples that are being constructed you
will hardly ever see any of those
carvings beautiful carvings of human
shapes
why is it so that is very perplexing i
think we are now all abrahamised
uh we are all secularized we should not
draw the human shape anywhere and
we seem to be very ashamed of the human
human form we should not show the human
form especially wearing less clothes our
ancestors do you used to practice that
but we are now
modern we wear clothes we don't show any
part of the body and that sort of thing
we kind of have become deracinated we
are losing touch with our
ancestral culture
and that seems to be the reason why you
don't see
too many
sculptures on the walls of temples which
is very it's very sad and also it may
also be because partially that
we don't have good
artisans anymore who can produce that
sculpture of the of that caliber that
may also be a reason for that but at
least we should attempt to do that
so it's disappointing that temples are
now being
see first of all
hardly any new temples are being built
you will see other structures
mushrooming all over the country but
hindu temples very few are being built
today
and even those that are that are being
built you will see them like they're
very plain
and there's nothing
really magnificent about them which is
which is disappointing
okay ishwar roshan says in south korea
the majority of the population has no
religion and are unaffiliated
why did they have no religion
that's another interesting question i
think more than 20 of south koreans are
christians actually practicing
christians and they even send
missionaries to other countries
including india to to
to proselytize and to preach their
religion but uh i am not sure about the
statistics but if you what you say is
correct then
it is interesting and strange that
the majority of the koreans have no
religion
so let's understand what happened
korea was traditionally a buddhist
country right we know that
korea has been above this country now
now what happened is that korea got got
entangled
in
in the korean war which was essentially
a tussle for
influence
in the korean peninsula between the
americans and the russians and the
chinese on one side you are the russians
and the chinese
the chinese essentially supported by the
russians the ussr on the other hand you
had the americans the americans are the
big objective don't let communism spread
anywhere in the world so that's why they
wanted to uh hold on to korea
and the chinese wanted to turn korea
into the strategic backyard and to give
them more depth strategic depth
and to use it as as a bulwark against
the americans
so that's where this entire conflict
happened the korean war i think it was
in the 1950s it was a terrible thing it
devastated korea what happened at the
end is that there was this
uh
cease-fire line that was drawn
which gave rise to two nations north
korea and south korea north korea is
communist it is completely atheistic
because of communism and south korea is
essentially under u.s protection or u.s
occupation whichever way you want to see
it
so south korea was
devastated in the korean war
completely impoverished you had
starvation
and all that
then the americans
kind of assisted the koreans in
rebuilding for 20 years you had a de
facto dictatorship in south korea and
you had a great deal of american
influence in korea in south korea and
when you have american influence you're
going to have the associated missionary
activities and all that
so the koreans were starving and
extremely poor they saw the americans
very powerful very rich etc and they
were all christians and missionaries so
many of them converted to christianity
i think like i said more than 20 of
korean south koreans today would be
christians and maybe it is also the
influence of the americans that led
to other koreans lots of them abandoning
their ancestral culture and becoming
atheists unaffiliated whatever maybe
they saw that
maybe they felt
uh that buddhism is pointless or or
maybe it's not as great as
as atheism so i'm just speculating but
it's all
something that happened after the korean
war so it's all because of external
influences if the koreans had been left
alone they had not been interfered with
and and
manipulated from outside by the
soviets
by the chinese by the americans if they
had just left
being left independent then i don't
think anything of the sort would have
happened there korea would have still
been
a buddhist nation
but that's how it works that's how
external influence works that's how
external interference works it
messes with your culture it messes with
your values your worldview and
everything else
okay this is by lelouch
can every indian when in school life be
trained in army camps for one to two
years
so that they may develop patriotism and
respect for the nation and grow up to be
mature
and physically fit citizens in india
well it's not a bad idea if you look at
israeli
they all
every israeli citizen has to undergo
compulsory military practice i think
it's three years if i'm not mistaken i
may be wrong but i think it's three
years
so everybody
uh
spends a certain time as a soldier
they actually serve as a soldier not
just training but actual service
and that teaches them discipline
physical fitness the value
of
the freedom that you enjoy and all those
things
when it comes to india
i wonder how many students
india has at any given point in time i
mean
young adult students 18 plus
india must be having tens maybe hundreds
of millions
of
students of that age
let's let's assume it's a hundred
million students at any given point in
time
now how are we going to arrange
organized army camps for a hundred
million students
the indian army must have a strength of
maybe two million
i'm not sure what's the exact number two
three million at most
how will they organize training camps
for a hundred million students so there
you see the problem of scale
it becomes completely impractical
to even think of this imagine how many
resources you will have to spend
your entire army will be engaged in
training people instead of
serving on the borders and doing
whatever is required
so that's why it's an impractical uh
idea it's not a bad idea but
unfortunately given the resources we
have and given the scale of the
operation it becomes completely
impractical what we can do actually
is have the ncc kind of training
compulsory or optional whatever for
everybody make it available to all
students so that they can
so that they can
partake in an experience of the military
life
and not just marching and saluting
another but actual weapons training
perhaps
you know or something similar to that so
maybe that could
uh
help them imbibe some of the discipline
that you find in the army and some of
the values
and
and the and the appreciation
of what it takes to keep india free and
safe
so maybe that is something that can be
thought of but but uh organizing army
training for all of them will be really
really impractical given the kind of
scale that is required but it's not a
bad idea something like that can
certainly be thought of
we already have we already have the ncc
etc that people
that some students
join in college national cadet
cadet
core
so maybe that can be modernized i think
it's still a 20th century kind of
institution they still use those
303 bore rifles that were used in the
first world war so maybe it can be
modernized and upgraded a little bit and
maybe that can be used to
to impart that sort of discipline and
training
among youngsters
okay abhishek says why
these days it has become cool for
youngsters to drink and smoke all my
friends started this and they keep
forcing me to drink and smoke
what should i do and what should i say
to them
so abhishek what you need is new friends
the thing is this
the people who surround you day in and
day out they're going to influence you
and they're going to shape who you are
you are the average of the you know it's
it's a cliche isn't it that you are the
average of the five people closest to
you
so if you have
negative people around you you're gonna
have negative thoughts all the time
if you have really positive
forward-looking people around you big
achievers you're gonna become like them
so if your friends
are people who drink and smoke
and they are the kind of people who want
to force you to do something you don't
want to do you need new friends
those friends are not good for you
they're not good for themselves also
and if they are forcing you to do
something bad and forcing you to do
something you don't want to do they are
not your friends they are actually your
enemies
so what you need to do is get new
friends you need to find a way to remove
these people from your
from your life
in some way or the other
i don't think it's
has it become cool for youngsters to
smoke and drink maybe because of the
media smoking not so much but maybe
drinking perhaps this pub culture it's
cool it's hip to drink and go to
go to bars and all that i i i don't
think it's good at all
so all i can say is
you need to cut these people out of your
life
okay two questions abhishek says we can
we constantly feel emotions and they
continually infect our thinking
please please guide us how to deal with
negative thinking patterns in stressful
circumstances
when we feel psychologically alone
abandoned and in moments of great doubt
lots of young students are irrational
and impatient some commit suicide
many of them start alcoholism in the
younger age
please guide us and the other one is
what are your viewpoints on the various
changes and challenges faced by a dollar
cent
when you were in a dollar cent how did
you deal with them and what message
would you like to give the dollar since
of today
so the number one problem you face as a
teenager as an adolescent is you feel
confused you feel lost
you don't know what the future holds
you don't know what is the right path
for you there are so many different
options all confusing all scary
society has these expectations from you
your family has these expectations for
you from you you don't understand
yourself properly you don't
want certain things but you are being
pushed in some directions and when you
lose control of your life in this manner
it's what causes depression it's when
you see that you have no future that you
want when whatever future is in front of
you is something you don't want
so that's what causes depression and all
that so what i would say is that
um
what you need is you need to have first
of all
as a teenager as early as possible you
have to find a way to understand who you
really are you have to try to understand
yourself first because most people go
through their entire life never
understanding them themselves
so if you have to find a way to
understand yourself you have to
introspect spend some time away from
other people
think about yourself who you are what
are your likes dislikes what are the
feelings what are your aptitudes what
are your strengths weaknesses that's the
first thing you need to understand
secondly you have to understand that you
are in this world to live a life that is
best for yourself you are not in the
world to please other people
now when you are young you are powerless
because other people
family etc will force you in certain
directions fine
let it happen but you should have a big
objective
a big objective
by by that i mean you should you should
have a certain objective
about where you want to be
when you're let's say 30 years old so
let's say you're 16 now you're confused
but give yourself a big goal that when i
am 30 years old i want to have achieved
this this this
and i want to have earned this this is
this amount of money give yourself
that sort of an objective when you have
an objective like that
then you will always feel that even if
something goes wrong right now
temporarily i still have time to reach
there and remember remember this it's
okay to make mistakes it's okay to fail
when you're young you should make lots
of small mistakes
and you should have lots of small
failures because they teach you a lot
and
remember this
don't make enormous mistakes
make small mistakes lots of small
mistakes how do you do that
understand
what risk taking is
let me give you an example i'm not
saying do this but i'm giving an example
let's say at the age of 16
hypothetically you have one lakh rupees
in your savings account
what is a huge stupid risk risk
it is putting all of that in the stock
market everything that is a catastrophic
risk that can wipe out your bank balance
what is a good risk
put 10 000 rupees out of that one lakh
in stock market and play around and see
how it works even if you lose all of
that no big deal so that's how you make
small mistakes and that's how we learn
from those mistakes iteratively
so that is the approach you need to have
in life as a youngster
understand that it is perfectly fine to
make mistakes it's perfectly fine to
have some failures early on in life have
failures it's okay don't do well in a
few exams doesn't matter it's not the
end of the world the future has lots and
lots of options in front of you you may
not be able to see them today but they
are there and always have a big big goal
in front of you 15 years down the line
maybe when you're 30. if you have this
sort of approach
and if you surround yourself with
positive thinking people or if you read
positive things if you watch positive
podcasts etc then you will stay positive
and stay away from bad habits don't
smoke don't drink
go to the gym
work out whether you're a boy whether
you're a girl go to the gym and work out
lift weights
get strong if you're a physically strong
person you'll be mentally strong so
these are some of the things i can tell
and i wish all of you the best of luck i
hope that many of you are going to be
the future leaders of india in the world
just go for it
okay let's take one more question the
question is two questions science
fiction what are some science fiction um
novels for a beginner in science and do
you like science fiction books if yes
can you mention some names
i
love science fiction when i was a kid
when i was a teenager even as a young
adult all i wanted to read is science
fiction it's the most interesting genre
for me now i read all kinds of things
but
originally it was all science fiction so
what can i suggest as beginner science
fiction i can suggest the hitched
hiker's guide to the galaxy by douglas
adams the foundation series by isaac
asimov duned by frank herbert
um neuromancer william gibson jurassic
park michael crichton
h.p lovecraft at the mountains of
madness
uh starship troopers
ring world by larry niven
h.g wells had the war of the worlds the
time machine
jule warren the french guy 20 000
leagues under the sea
and arthur c clarke great writer uh 2001
a space odyssey so these are some of the
uh
books i can suggest if you are
interested in science fiction i found
those books really interesting
great great writing
so that's some
some examples of science fiction in case
you want to get
started
okay this is the last question for today
this is by nandita sharma why akshay
bhullar is getting so much privilege on
this channel
each and every question that he asks
gets picked by you instantly
you have said that all people on this
channel will be treated equally then why
this is my question for you okay fine i
think i may have clarified this before
but let me clarify again
yes i have said that each and every
person will be treated equally see what
happened when i started the channel in
the beginning
is in the live chats i used to have this
thing called super chats you will see
this on many other channels so people
will pay money to ask that question and
their question is visible in bright
color so it gets picked up automatically
because it's very so visible
so that was i realized very quickly it
was causing a divide among my viewers
it was pitting those who could afford to
pay money against those youngsters who
had no money when you were a teenager
when you were 20 years old you had no
money to pay like this so it was
creating a divide among my viewers so
that's why i switched off this option of
super chats on my channel i will never
have super chats i will never take money
to answer questions that is what i mean
by
everybody will be treated the same so
everybody gets the same opportunity to
ask questions that is called
what is it called it's called equality
of opportunity everybody gets the same
opportunity now why do i pick certain
questions more than ever rather than
other other questions
it's because
i respect my audience
see the thing is this
if if somebody pays you gives you three
three seconds of their attention it's a
big privilege
and my audience
watches my channel for thousands of
hours of watch time
so that is a huge privilege my audience
is giving me they are spending their
precious valuable time on my channel and
i will respect them by respecting their
time how will i respect the time by
giving them the highest return on
investment
on and the highest value for the time by
selecting the best questions
see that's how it works this i'm not
doing a lottery here but i will pick up
some random questions and answer them
all i will
pick up the best questions because i
have certain standards on this channel
it's called
discernment i will judge
quality of the questions and then i will
pick up those questions so this is not
an experiment in socialism and marxism
where everybody goes down to a certain
level of mediocrity
right this is i believe in meritocracy
in meritocracy everybody gets to ask the
questions everybody is treated the same
but then
the best questions are picked up it's
like saying teach your teacher you said
everybody will be treated equal so why
isn't everybody getting first first
rank right
so
that is the the philosophy and there is
a reason why this channel is popular why
it is growing because it has quality it
has standards
right so that is what i do i give
everybody the opportunity to ask the
question but i pick only the best
questions and the questions that
interest me obviously right i decide
that
so if you want your question to be
selected
you will have to rise to the quality of
this show of the ask abij your question
should be that interesting that good if
you ask me a question that is so good i
can't ignore it i will pick the question
make me an offer i can't refuse
so i hope that answers this question
okay i think i've run out of all the
questions i've selected now
shall i take a couple of minutes of of
uh
live chat questions
i have deleted a comment of yours
are you sure
you know what youtube deletes lots of
comments the algorithm
deletes comments based on the kind of
words you use
yeah okay so that's what i can say
what else do we have anything else
i can see thousands of comments i'm not
sure if i can pick any of those right
now
lots of questions are repeated yes i
will repeat certain questions because i
answer every time i take a question i
answer it in different ways and many of
the new viewers
have not seen my older answers so that's
why i sometimes take questions that are
repeated that is for me to decide
all right
um
yeah okay i think i think i'm
i'm done for today it's almost two hours
so thank you everybody for your
questions
keep asking me great questions i will
pick the best questions always and only
the best questions i get thousands of
questions per week my
objective is to give you all the best
value
not by taking everybody's questions at
random but by taking the best questions
so that you will all learn something
that will hopefully be valuable to you i
hope that even 20 years in the future
when people see these these live streams
on the live in the short clips they will
still find something of value and
something that could be relevant even 20
years in the future that's why i only
pick selected questions
all right
thank you very much everybody thank you
very much for your time and i will see
you again tomorrow tomorrow is a live
chat session
so come ready with your questions and i
will see you tomorrow
thank you take care
bye